Jiawei Gu

LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/jiawei-gu/ | GitHub: https://github.com/jiawku

Cell: (801)-637-4021 | Email: jiawku17@gmail.com | Salt Lake City, UT

Summary

I had **fours** years experience of **data analysis and engineering** in the realm of biocomputing in academic and industry. I obtained a **MS in computer science** and a **MS in biology** from University of Texas at Dallas. With a Certificate from **Amazon Web Service**, I can boost your data analysis and engineering on the cloud.

Education

01/2017-05/2018

MS, Computer Science; University of Texas at Dallas(UTD); 3.91/4

08/2013-12/2016

MS, Bioinformatic; University of Texas at Dallas(UTD); 3.73/4

Proficient Skills

Programming languages

Python, Java, JavaScript, C++, R, SAS, SQL, PHP, Bash

Frameworks & Tools

- BigData: Apache Spark, Apache Hadoop
- Web: MEAN stack(MongoDB, Express JS, Angular JS, Node.js), Java Spring
- Deep Learning: TensorFlow, Keras
- · Containerization: Docker, Kubernetes
- Cloud Service: Amazon Web Service(certified)

Certification

• AWS Certified Solutions Architect - Associate

Credential ID: 6WQVVZSKE24EQLK9

- Coursera Deep Learning Specialization
- SAS Certified Base & Advanced Programmer for SAS 9
- · edX Verified Certificate for Big Data Analysis with Apache Spark

Experience

Bioinformatics Analyst, Navican Genomics, Inc. Salt Lake City, 08/2018-Present

Production & Automation

- o Daily clinical control sequencing quality assurance.
- Implemented and improved the Tumor Mutation Burden(TMB) calculation algorithm within the bioinformatics team inspired by
- Built an automated pipeline for clinical control assurance in python. It connected multiple cloud service platforms(Philips IntelliSpace Genomics Medicine, SalesForce, SeraCare IQ, Slack, and Amazon AWS) via REST API.
- Created an Illumina BaseSpace Native APP for sequencing quality control using Docker.

• Data Engineering

- Created tools to query and clean data from cloud service platforms (Philips IntelliSpace Genomics Medicine, SalesForce, Clarity LIMS) via REST API for ETL and R&D.
- Designed a **Postgresql Database** to store bioinformatics data.

Data Analysis

- o Implemented and run validation workflows for Illumina TruSight™ Tumor 170 Sequencing Assay.
- Designed **statistical tests** for lab operation quality metrics.
- Help with other ad-hoc data analysis requests.

Research Assistant, Biology Department, UTD 01/2014-12/2016

I focused on the research of Next-Generation Sequencing analysis, especially on ChIP-seq, RNA-seq, and ChIA-PET Seq result analysis, and using machine learning tools to analyze and predict from data.

- Machine Learning Prediction for RNA-chromosome interaction
 - Collect genomic and epigenomic data from online resources by a self coded web crawler.
 - o Cleaned data and used Random Shuffle to generate more negative data points.
 - Applied Support Vector Machine to generate a model
- DNA Sequencing Analysis of Brg1 in Cancer Cell, UTD
 - Built pipelines for data process and ChIP-seq analysis using Linux bash shell
 - Implemented a protein binding motif scan and enrichment analysis program in R
 - Analyzed and Visualized data in R and Python
 - **Article publication**: Shi, X., et al. "SMARCA4/Brg1 coordinates genetic and epigenetic networks underlying Shhtype medulloblastoma development." Oncogene (2016).

Side Projects

Dog Breed Identification, Kaggle.com 05/2018

- A Kaggle machine learning competition Project
- Design and built a **convolutional neural network(CNN)** in **keras** to determine the breed of a dog in an image (total 120 breeds)
- Applied a integrated model of Xception and InceptionV3 to extract bottleneck features from image
- Used three fully connected layers with drop out and batch normalization to get predicted probabilities
- Used **Adam** optimization algorithm to train the final model with **cross entropy** as loss function
- Get the final validation accuracy of 99.76%, can rank 102 out of 1286 teams